[Music]
Hey, hey, hey.
Heat.
[Music]
Hey. Hey. Hey.
Hello, good evening, good day everybody
and welcome back to the Ask a Bidget
show. This is the geopolitics edition,
super chat edition and live chat
edition. So let's see who is there on
the live chat. Today I will only take
questions about geopolitics. Yesterday
we did a history live stream. I hope
that was interesting. Today it's going
to be only geopolitics. Let's see who is
there on the live chat. I can see a
tulle from Alman from Germany. Bos sir
Shri Ramchandra Raar Vanch Gada Aayush
Singh uh Amisha Mishra anonymous
scientist Bju Mystic SK Jri Krishna
Suhas Red Srai Aayush Yadav Sundep Nay
Rahul Sharma Astrodude Mr. Saxa from
Ireland.
Uh, Mlevin,
uh, Ary Kush, Suas, Reddi, Vlatimir,
Putin, Hensy, Penguin, Jant, Anupam, Ja,
Swall, City, Slicker, Just Some Nut,
Shashank, Koshik, Negro, Shiva, Sai,
Mystic, SK, Kuml, Dark Knight,
Geopolitical, Dubet, Good evening. Who
else do we have? Nishant Chri, Dakshvara
from Gujarat, Arian Sharma, Vanchi
Kaleim, General Subutai, Swami Jan from
Jaipur, Duv Durya, Romesh Kunti, Gorla,
Adwe, Dave, Sepak, Rajumar, Arya,
Shanks, Jayant, Vinay from London,
Rahul, Pera, Satyam, Gupta,
Geopolitic again from Indor, Swami, Jay,
Pratam, Sharma, Ashugam, Animals for
Laugh, Prashant Singh, Deep P Sharma Vin
and Roihai Negro Pragya Sunil Seagal
Satellite Binit from Siliguri. Hello
Hoola Vinay from London. Freedom from
outcome from Canada. Vikash PJ Karthika
Singh Rajput.
Uh the way Rajat Panar Rocky Shivani
Maheshwari
Shanks
Saita Reddi Shivasai Dave Hayes Ankita
Om Praash Deepanka Roy Ajinka 2004
Sangeit Shiras Vikash PJ and everybody
else good evening good day to all of you
wherever you are in the world and thank
you so much for joining this live stream
and now let us get going with the
questions. Ravi Kumar is from Andhra
Pradesh as well. Well, thank you so much
everybody for for being on the live
chat. Let's uh let's take some
questions. All right.
Okay. Uh once again, let me remind you
all I'm going to only take questions
from geopolitics today. So, please don't
give other questions otherwise it's
going to be a waste. All right. So,
ICMBBS says, "Are tariff hurdles the
double-edged sword that India needs?
Short-term pain that forges long-term
global resilience?"
Well, it certainly is a wake-up call for
India and it's an opportunity for India
to execute great reforms in the country
because the country does need that for
sure. See what the tariffs do is that
they are going to hamper India's exports
to the US. What are tariffs? Let's say
you are an exporter. I am an American
importer and I want to buy something
from you. Let's say you are you are an
Indian exporter. Let's say you are uh
and I'm an American importer and I have
given you a contract for a hund00
million worth of let's say watches
completely hypothetical example don't
take it literally but you get the point
so you are going to manufacture a h 100
million sorry a million dollars worth of
watches you're going to sell it to me
now Trump has imposed 50% tariffs on
India what that means is that the moment
you send me the consignment of watches
that I have paid for the moment I
receive the consignment
I'm going to have to pay the US
administration, the US government 50% of
the cost of of the price of my shipment.
So, I paid you a million dollars. Now,
I'm going to pay have to pay the US
government half a million dollars.
And that that makes it extremely bad for
business for me. So, I'm going to have
to reconsider now that if I'm going to
have instead of spending just a million,
I'm going to have to spend 1.5 million
every time for something that costs a
million. It's going to really affect my
business, won't it? So then I'll say
okay, I'll stop importing from you. It's
not it's not good business. So I'll
import from somebody else from some
other country. So it's going to hamper
it's going to hurt India's exposed to
the US. The US is the world's biggest
consumer market. Right? So India is now
going to have to look for alternatives
if the exports to the US dry out because
it it's it's no longer good business
sense for Americans to American
companies to import goods and services
from India. So then it deprivives India
of access to the world's biggest
consumer market
and that's that's a problem. So India
will have to now look for alternatives.
Where do we look for alternative
alternatives? The EU, the Gulf region,
maybe China but China is not an import
oriented market. It's an export oriented
market. So what do we do? So it's going
to then one option is that we we
manufacture for our own population for
our own citizens a consumption-driven
economy. But then our citizens are poor.
Our GDP per capita is I don't know
whatever it is pretty low, very low.
It's like it's like African countries.
It is what it is, right? So what do we
do about this? For that we need to raise
our GDP, raise our raise the the the
earning standards etc. of our
population. For that you need tremendous
uh reforms.
You need to boost you need to boost the
ease of doing business, the
boost the manufacturing sector. so many
so many things. So you need deep
reforms, broad-ranging reforms but uh
reforms is difficult. I mean if you to
to for example if the government wants
to invest money in certain sectors and
all that they're going to have to find
the money from somewhere we have a lot
of money in the country but all the
money is being used for various freebie
schemes largely ba yoja and god know god
knows what else yojna and if the
government stops doing those those yojas
next election end of story because the
Indian public is is so addicted so
hooked to freebies that it's going to be
a disaster for the government so that's
the problem that India faces that's the
problem. Um but India does need reforms
and this is the greatest of of of
opportunities for India to to do uh deep
and broad reforms and if we do it right,
if the government does it right, then in
the next 20 years we're going to be we
will hopefully be a much larger much
stronger economy. So it's not going to
be short-term pain, it's going to be
medium-term pain like 10 20 years. But
yeah, if so India, the government of
India, Prime Minister Modi has already
made the choice that we will not cave
into the US. We will not join the
illustrious list of American vasals
whose heads adorn the corridors
of the west wing. We're not going to do
that. So then in that case if if we made
the choice then we need to execute the
reform. So it's a great opportunity for
India to execute big reforms big bang
reforms if the government has the can do
it and if that is done then in maybe in
20 years we're going to be a whole
different beast. So it's going to be a
period of uh well it's a stressful
period for India for a while.
Sait says will Latin America tilt
towards China's orbit? Well not too
much. See the Chinese are already in
Latin America. They've been around for a
long time like 15 years at least
probably 20 years. I remember about
around 2010 or so I had there was this
BBC documentary the Chinese are coming
or something about about China's
investments in Latin America in Brazil
in Africa and so on and it portrayed
those investments in a in rather in a
rather negative light obviously uh the
Chinese are already there and uh they
are investing in various raw materials
sectors in Latin America Latin America
you know Brazil is a gigantic country
much larger than India uh lots of it's
it's rich in resources. The Chinese want
the resources. There are other countries
in Latin America that are rich in
lithium and cobalt and whatever else.
The Chinese want that and the Chinese
will will pay good money will pay top
dollar for those raw materials. So it
makes sense for these countries to deal
with China. Does it mean that these
countries are tilting towards China's
orbit? I'm not really sure about that.
The US won't let that happen. Not not
too far. Uh but Brazil is part of
bricks. So there is that. So, it's going
to be a balancing act.
Anonymous scientist says Trump has
appointed Sergio Gore as ambassador to
India and special envoy for South and
Central Asia. Is it bad news for India
because he will engage with Pakistan and
Bangladesh. Look, Trump essentially has
what he has done is he's tried to
appoint a viceroy for India. a guy in
with with Sergio Gore they the US
government is saying India will be in
safe hands hey by the way we not in your
hands he's an envoy right but but that's
the deal so they they've essentially
appointed hopefully from their
perspective a viceroy for India so this
is an attempt to rehyenate India and
Pakistan to drag India down to the level
of Pakistan so Trump is trying to bring
Pakistan up and he wants to drag India
down so then both can be equated
And this individual, Sergio Gore, who is
going to be the next ambassador, he's
the special, he's also the special envoy
for South Asia, whatever the hell that
means, and Central Asia. Um, yeah. So,
South Asia from the US State
Department's perspective, it is the
Indian subcontinent, but they don't call
it the Indian subcontinent. They call it
South Asia because they want to erase
the Indian identity of the place. So,
within South Asia, you have Pakistan,
Bangladesh, all all of that, right? Sri
Lanka, Nepal, Bhutan, Maldi, whatever
else you could imagine. Uh Afghanistan
possibly. Yeah, it should be there.
Yeah. Uh yeah. So he's going to engage
with Pakistan and he's going to engage
with Bangladesh. He's going to be
stationed in Delhi and in Delhi the US
has one of the one of its biggest
embassies anywhere in the world. So they
have a big staff there. And uh yeah,
he's going to essentially oversee the
entire region as as Trump's viceroy to
the region. That sort of thing. Is it
bad news? So the appointment of Sergio
Gore per se is not bad news for India.
The the attitude of the Trump regime is
the bad news for India. They are
hellbent hellbent on rehyenating India
and Pakistan. And that's going to be an
issue that we're going to have to deal
with the next three and a half or so
years. And then after Trump is gone and
some other president comes to power,
we'll have to see how that that regime u
approaches uh relations towards with
India. We'll have to see about that. But
overall, I don't think this is a much
better uh US ambassadorial appointee
compared to let's say Eric Garcetti who
was here for some time ago is gone.
So now there's going to be a process.
He's going to be he's going to have to
be vetted by Congress and so on. But
yeah, eventually I suppose it will land
in Delhi.
MK says why didn't the USSR make the CCP
its vasal given the CCP's revolution?
Chinese Communist Party's revolution
would not have succeeded without Soviet
help. You see the Chinese Communist
Party
was led by Maoong. North Tong was a very
cany, very, very, very sharp guy and he
himself had imperial ambitions for China
and he held Joseph Stalin in the highest
regard and as long as Stalin was the the
head was the ruler of the USSR, China
was very differential towards the USSR
and the USSR did extend a lot of help to
China and possibly u you know with the
objective of of having China in their
orbit.
Now when you have a nation of the
gigantic size and scale of China, it's
very hard to make it a vasal. The same
problem exists with India. So that's why
there are nations who want to balconize
India and deal with each bit and piece
individually separately. So Mahatong was
very smart. He straight up went and
captured Tibet and it he was aided and
abetted by the Indian government of the
time who supplied the Chinese troops
with rice and because of of all of that
and because China started developing its
own industry and its military might
that's why it was not that easy for the
USSR to make the CCP its to make China's
wasal and after the death of Stalin you
had uh Kruef who came to power and
that's where the strife started so then
Mahatong took a whole different
trajectory he was no longer that aligned
with the USSR and that that's what
annoyed the USSR and then there were
these border clashes in the far east of
of Russia and China the the Usuri river
clashes which made the two nations go
completely diver diver on divergent
trajectories this was the Senos Soviet
split so it's not like if I want to make
somebody my vasal I'm going to succeed
it's not that easy right other if if if
it's a nation like China they will not
want you to make the to be to be your
vasal so it's not like okay I have
decided he will be my masal vasal so
you'll be so it will happen they tried
Stalin did not try that hard but Krisha
probably wanted to have that happen and
did not work out so it's not like just
because I want this to happen it's going
to happen you can try but it may fail
because the other side is strong and
that is how it went
uh anonymous scientist says is ra I a
possibility now China is cozying up to
India and India is also carefully
working with China
okay so is China cozying up with India?
Is China
behaving in a friendly manner with India
is what we have to ask ourselves.
What would be
Chinese overtures of friendship?
Is it like verbal overtures?
Indians have this great great love for
words. Someone says nice words about you
and you're like, "Oh my god, we are best
friends." No. In geopolitics, words
don't matter. You can say all kinds of
nice things but what you do on the
ground that action is what matters.
China is still consolidating its
positions on the north bank etc of the
Bangong lake. They are still
consolidating their positions militarily
um in Chinese occupied Tibet and across
the border with Ladak and Arunachal
Pradesh. They are doing all of that.
They have offered no uh concessions to
India in terms of demarcation of of of
the border. They have done none of these
things. What is the crucial issue when
it comes to India China relations?
What's the central problem? It's the
boundary issue. What is the India China
border? Right now it's India and Chinese
occupied Tibet. That border, right? And
it's undefined. It's undemarcated.
Now, if you want stability in relations,
if you want actual uh cozying up, then
you want that issue to be settled first.
As long as that issue exists and it's
open, there's going to be tension. And
that's the central problem in the in in
the relationship between the two
countries. Has China taken any steps
to resolve the border issue? They
they're taking no such steps. It's just
words.
Yeah. The flights are flights are
resuming between the two countries and
the Chinese have allowed the Indian
pilgrims to go to Kailash Manor. All
those nice little things they are doing.
But the central issue still remains,
right? So as far as I'm concerned,
nothing has happened.
Yeah, Prime Minister Modi is going to
China at the end of this month. He he'll
probably meet with President Jinping. Uh
Mr. Wangi was in Delhi a few days ago to
probably lay the groundwork for uh Prime
Minister Modi's visit and so on. It's
good that the two leaders are going to
be meeting on and off now and tensions
are lower, but the central issue isn't
resolved. And as long as that issue
resolves, there's always the possibility
of some kind of disaster on the border
because some there was some
miscommunication or or misunderstanding
between the two sides
on on the ground between the two armies.
Then what do you do? So that issue is a
central issue and the Chinese keep want
to keep it open. As long as that's the
case, it's it's just uh tactical
nonsense. There's nothing really
happening on the ground. So is RC a
possibility? Right now it's far from a
possibility.
RS will be seen together more often. It
doesn't mean that they're going to work
together as a coalition, as an alliance.
That is far from happening. Far from
happening.
Geopolitical Dubet says, "Does China
truly want the Ukraine war to end?"
Look, first of all, China cannot affect
the outcome of the Ukraine war. It's
entirely Russia-driven. But look, what
does it mean? What does this war mean
for China? This this war has been pretty
beneficial for China because it has
completely isolated Russia from the
West. The West has imposed every
sanction imaginable on China because of
which I beg your pardon on Russia.
Right. The west has isolated Russia. The
west has imposed every possible sanction
that you can imagine on Russia because
of which Russia has become pretty
strongly dependent on China and that's
great for China. That's great.
And the Chinese have been selling Russia
various kinds of equipment or maybe
indirectly through other countries or
whatever. Russia has been selling China
lots of oil, more oil than they are
selling us, okay, at discounted rates.
It's been great for China and if this
war ends up with the further
destabilization of the west and the f
further weakening of the EU and the west
overall it's great for China. Now if the
war ends and the west once again
consolidates then it's a not such a
great thing for China.
Um so it will so China most likely will
want this war to continue.
It will keep Russia isolated. It will
keep Russia more and more from their
perspective hopefully dependent on China
and that's good for China. So probably
China would will be happy if this war
kind of meanders continues for another
couple of years and and battle lines are
are are further entrenched and that's
the opposite of what Donald Trump wants
because he's desperate for the war to
end for a ceasefire and that's not
happening.
Pavan says what's GDP PPP what does it
indicate and what does it have any
actual significance for example China 40
trillion US 30 trillion India 17
trillion is it's purchasing power parity
um it's uh it's about the true
purchasing power of your currency
based on your GD on on your income
levels and all that. So for example, if
I go to Switzerland and I want to buy a
bottle of water, it may cost me about
$40.
Okay, giving a rough example, it may not
exactly cost $40. It may cost you $35,
something like that. So a bottle, a half
liter bottle hypothetically of water in
Switzerland will cost about $35.
In India, it will cost you 15 rupees.
You see the the price difference for
each item for the same item the same
quantity of water in India costs 15
rupees
which is what
which is about what? It's about 15 cents
in US dollar terms roughly
and in Switzerland it costs $35.
So the Swiss cost if it's let's say it's
40 it's about 2,000 times more than
India if my math is right. I'm just
doing it on the fly. So you see the
difference in purchasing power. So if if
the Swiss GDP per capita is like $50,000
per year and India's GDP per capita is
like 2,500 3,000. And yet with that
little money, $3,000 per year, the
average Indian can buy much more
possibly compared to what the Swiss can
buy. I'm just giving a very very rough
dirty example, but I hope you get the
the point. So if you base your
calculations on that purchasing power of
your currency and how much your your
income is and what the prices of various
commodities are in India and other
countries then you come up with a whole
different set of criteria and a whole
different set of figures and that's GDP
GDP you know that's how it works. So
from that perspective, China is 40
trillion, India is 30 trillion, US is 30
trillion, India is 17 trillion. That's a
different way of looking at it.
Sax
says, can bricks make their own own
currency to trade with themselves? If
yes, can then India can bring the UPI
technology stuff to distribute it? Is it
practically possible? Okay, there's been
a lot of talk of of bricks currency and
lots of Indians seem to be in favor of
that. uh so a brrics currency would be a
currency that's a common currency
between a number of nations
originally you had five bricks nations
Brazil India Brazil Russia India China
and South Africa and now there are more
countries that have joined bricks so
let's say whatever the number is let's
say it's 10 countries let's say
hypothetically 10 countries it may be
more maybe less I don't remember exactly
so if you have a common currency it
means
that all the countries will obviously u
transact only in that currency
But such experiments have happened in
the past.
The best example is the European Union.
Their currency is the euro. Yes. Well,
you will find that the euro is
essentially a rebranded Deutsche mark.
The Deutsch mark used to be the currency
of Germany. Germany was the most
powerful and still is the most powerful
economy in Europe.
So when the euro was created, it
essentially became a substitute for the
Deutsch mark and it essentially
continues the dominance of Germany in
the European Union. So when you have a
coalition of nations who come up with a
common currency, it's going to end up
being
more favorable towards
the the most towards the largest economy
in the coalition. it's going to give
them the most benefits and the other
smaller economies will kind of become
dependent on the larger economy. So then
if you have a common currency, where is
the common bank going to be like going
to be situated? See if you if you lose
control over currency, you lose your
economic sovereignty. Do you understand
that? You lose your economic
sovereignty. One of the reasons why the
EU nations are not sovereign nations is
because they have no no control over
their economies because they don't have
a currency of their own. They don't
control the currency.
That's why that's one reason why the EU
nations are are not sovereign nations.
It's pulled sovereignty. And when
sovereignty is pulled, there's a center
of power somewhere. And that center of
power controls a lot about what happens
with your economy or that that guy's
economy. So, do we want to be in a
position where China, the largest
economy in bricks, ends up controlling
our economy? Do you want that? Yeah. So,
think about it like this. I don't think
the bricks currency is a good idea for
us.
I don't think it's a good idea. UPI
technology, we can anyway use it. I
mean, we can export it to other
countries and and gain some benefit out
of it, you know, to see how to make it
feasible. So even if you you export UPI
technology to China and they are dealing
in yuan maybe they can use it in yuan
right but I don't think the bricks
currency is a very good idea unless
unless we we have very very stringent uh
terms on it
sit says how fragile is middle east be
well it depends on the main powerful
nations look if you look at middle east
okay let's go let's go to the map and
let's look at uh the region so that we
understand what the situation is like
okay let's go to the Middle East so the
Middle East essentially is said to start
from uh Iran
so Iran westwards we have the Middle
East which includes the Saudi the the
Arabian Peninsula which is Oman Yemen
UAE uh Bahrain Qatar Saudi Arabia
then you also have Jordan, Syria, Iraq
and uh Israel Lebanon right and Sabun
some would even include include Egypt in
that but maybe not. So this is the
region. Now who are the main actors? The
one is Saudi Arabia, right? The other is
UAE, pretty powerful economy. Then you
have Iran, a very powerful nation. Then
you have Iraq is a non- entity now
because of the American occupation,
which kind of still continues to some
extent. Syria is now a regime change
country. So it's it's done. It's just
like Iraq. But you have Israel. So the
main tension in the region is is Iran
versus Israel. Israel versus Iran. And
there's also also the Gaza issue and all
that. So Gaza is now under control. When
it comes to uh Israel, they have Gaza,
West Bank, all of that under control.
The West Bank of the River Jordan and
and Gaza, all of that. Uh they don't
have any major issues, the Israelis,
with their other neighbors. Everything
is more or less under control. Syria is
now a vasal of the US and Israel. So all
is good there. Egypt is under control.
The main problem from Israel's
perspective is is Iran. So now Israel is
worried that um Iran
is is attempting to to
become a nuclear power and Iran has
pretty good uh let's say allies in the
region. One is the the government in
Yemen that the so-called Houthi rebels.
They also have Hezbollah in Lebanon and
various Iraqi uh elements and so on. And
Israel also has power projection across
the region. So that is the main flash
point, Israel versus Iran. Uh is there a
possibility that something again may
flare up between the two countries? It's
always a possibility. So the previous
issue, the previous war between Iran and
Israel that happened recently, a month
or two ago, uh it was triggered by by
Israeli attacks on on Iran. So the
question is, will Israel attack Iran
again? Right now Iran doesn't look like
in a it's in a position to initiate a
war. maybe Israel can. So, it all
depends on is Israel's threat perception
and whether they decide to to initiate a
new war uh with Iran. That is the main
flash point right now in the Middle
East.
ICMBBS says, "Am I very right to be very
skeptical of fellow Indians getting
excited about the alliance with China,
the so-called alliance with China? I
think it's more than more a temporary
alignment of interests."
You are very right to be skeptical about
Indians starting starting to jump and
dance about this ra and this alliance
with China and and friendship with
China. Hindi I mean how many times do
you have to fall for the same old
same old routine? Hindi china
how many times do we have to fall for
it? Alliance. What alliance? Can you
have an alliance with a country with
whom
which claims your territory?
who refuses to demarcate your the common
border. You can't have an alliance. You
can at at best have a modus vivandhi
vivei which is kind of a living
arrangement. That's the best you can
have. The Chinese don't want to
demarcate the border with India. They
don't want that to happen.
And they are still consolidating their
military positions uh north of Ladak,
north of Arunachal in in occupied Tibet.
When you have that situation, what
alliance will you have? The best thing
is you can hope for maybe a few years of
peace because right now both nations
India and China are being uh are facing
heat from the Trump regime, right?
So maybe the Chinese right now they feel
like you know and and until I mean think
about it think about this. I mean I
cannot understand how naive Indians are.
How many months ago was May?
Two and a half months ago. Two and a
half months ago, China was passing real
time live intelligence to Pakistan when
the operation synd
it it it doesn't cease to astonish me.
every single day. New examples of
incredible naive.
I mean I I
I'm lost for words when I see how naive
Indians are. I'm lost for words.
Describe how naive Indians are.
Absolutely clueless people. Oh, China is
good now. China is friendly now. Oh, Mr.
Shei said some nice words. Mr. Wangi
said some nice things. Their ambassador
says nice things every day on Twitter.
So now we are friends.
So you are very right to be skeptical
about Indians getting excited about the
so-called alliance with China. Long way
to go. Long way to go. The first
precondition for normalization is a
demarcation of the border the India
Tibet border. That's the first
precondition.
Once that happens then we can consider
the possibility of a hypothetical
alliance. And for that also we have to
work on every single aspect and
parameter of what the parameters and
boundaries and and terms of the alliance
will be. You have to work it out step by
step in great exhaustive excruciating
detail. It's not like yeah you two spil
each other so your allies now. I mean
how naive can Indians be? Indians
imagine certain other countries are also
our allies.
Uh yeah so you are right to be very
skeptical sir.
Shivam Bakshi says, "Which country is
more likely to disintegrate, India or
China?" I think China is very
centralized. So maybe India is more
stable. My thoughts,
the more centralized a nation is, the
more stable it is, especially a large
nation with a powerful government. If
the government is powerful
and the system is centralized,
then it's very hard to destabilize that
government. If a system is already
decentralized, it's so easy to fragment
the system. It's the other way around
sir Shuam G.
If you have a weak government at the
center and this and the system is
centralized, then you can easily do a
regime change or a coup or whatever. But
when you have a powerful government at
the center and the whole system is under
one center, it's really hard to knock
that off. It's really hard to fragment
such a country. India has this great
system of federalism. Every state has
its own agenda. It's like trying to
herd, you know, hering sheep is very
easy because sheep are sheep. Now try
hering cats and see what happens. That's
India.
So if you really want to ask me which
country has a higher probability of
hypothetically hypothetically
disintegrating India
that's why the Americans do subnational
diplomacy. What is that?
I mean from the US perspective what's
the ideal situation? and India
balkcanized then they will deal with
each state individually and further
bulcanize and further uh puppeteer those
states that's why all those initiatives
are going on all the industrial scale uh
religious conversions and all the
dealing with various state level and
regional level political parties and and
whatever else they're doing right
fermenting separatism in the far east
far eastern states launching project K
cookie land for
religious angles, linguistic angles,
China doesn't have any of these issues
and China's CCP is incredibly powerful,
incredibly well entrenched. Even if
there's a regime change in the CCP and
hypothetically President Xenping is
ousted, there's going to be somebody
else who comes to power from the CCP
itself.
You see, it's not going to be somebody
from some other political party because
there is no other political party. The
CCP has ensured that. So that's a
situation. Which country is more
vulnerable? India or China? India is
more vulnerable. Understand that our
system by design makes India vulnerable.
This system of democracy and federalism,
it's the main threat to India.
Understand that.
Shivamakshi says, "Will Ukraine become
part of Russia in time after the war?"
uh in time. Well, it depends on what do
you mean by in time, right? If you say 6
months after the war
unlikely depending on first of all we
have to see how does the war end
whenever it does end. Right now the war
is not ending. We are nowhere close to a
ceasefire.
Trump is desperate for a ceasefire
because he is six month six months late
in his promise made to the American
people. On day one of the presidency I
will end the Ukraine war. Well, where is
the end of the Ukraine war? So, he's
desperate to end the Ukraine war. He
wants a ceasefire at any cost. And Mr.
Putin has been playing the other game,
the opposite game, slow war, frozen
conflict. Let it go on. Let it go on. It
serves his interests best. So, Mr. Putin
is in no hurry. Trump is in a tearing
hurry. He's in a tearing rush. So I
don't see this war ending anytime soon
unless they there are major concessions
that are given to Russia like a regime
change in Kiev and and more territory to
Russia and that sort of thing. It's not
going to happen anytime soon as far as I
see without major concessions. Mr. Putin
will not agree to a ceasefire. So let's
say a ceasefire happens
x number of months in the future.
What happens then? That will be a
partition of Ukraine. Where does the
partition happen? Does it happen where
the current lines are? Does it happen
further west? We don't know. Does it
happen along the river Niper?
Does it happen somewhere else?
The war will end with the partition of
Ukraine. But then what happens to the
rest of Ukraine? I suspect that some
rump state will remain. Some portion of
Ukraine that will not be part of Russia.
But a significant portion of Russia of
Ukraine is already part more or less de
facto part of Russia. And I suspect that
by the time the war ends, more
territories of Ukraine will be absorbed
by Russia.
I don't think they want the whole of
Ukraine, but I'm pretty certain they
they will at the end of the day they're
going to acquire more territories. So,
not the whole of Ukraine. I don't think
so, but much more than definitely
some more than than what Russia
currently occupies.
Makos says, "Mr. anonymous scientist uh
mentioned bricks in his tweet comments.
I kind of saw the the tweet by M which
he makes a mention of bricks. My
comments I think it's interesting. I
think it is a sign of rebellion against
the US. Okay. Like I've said so many
times, France is the only nation in NATO
and in the EU that has a quasi
independent foreign policy and they they
chafe they chafe at being under the yoke
of the Anglo-Saxons.
That's that's the worst situation for
them. The the French are a very proud
people. They have no love for the
Anglos. They fought the British, the
English for a thousand years. And uh you
know those memories persist and they
don't want to be under the thumb of the
Anglos. And currently they kind of are.
So it is great for France if they get to
collaborate and cooperate with India in
areas of mutual benefit. And there are
plenty of areas of mutual benefit and
mutual interest between India and
France. And now it appears that India is
going to go ahead with uh the joint
development of jet engines with Safh.
The the jet engines will be manufactured
in India produced entirely indigenously
in India with uh in a partnership with
Safh. So that's going to make a lot of
money for for France as well. And uh
there there's a lot of scope there's a
lot more scope for cooperation between
India and France in the future. Uh
France
and and Mr. Mak also wants a good
relations with with China and other
BRICS countries. So it makes sense that
he mentioned BRICS and and not in a in a
in a negative way and that is going to
upset Mr. Trump because Mr. Trump is is
very anti-bicks. So that is a direct
he's thumbming his nose at Trump and
he's also it kind of indicates uh the
direction in which the French India and
French France bricks relations are
poised to go in. So yeah,
geopolitical dubis is stuck in BCOM.
Look, I would be happy to answer these
questions but this is a geopolitics
liveream. Like I said in the beginning I
said let's discuss geopolitics today.
Okay. So I will not take this question.
I apologize but I will not see the
viewers are here for geopolitics. I will
only discuss geopolitics.
Okay. Amisha says, Abisha Mishra says,
"Why is Nepal opposing India China trade
deal?" J Shanker, sharp response to
Trump. If you have a problem buying oil
from India, don't buy it. What's my
take? So, these are two completely
different topics you're asking, but
let's just deal with this. Uh
Nepal, why is Nepal opposing the India
China trade deal? No, it's very simple.
Nepal claims some Indian territory,
Lipul or something.
uh and and India and China are resuming
trade across the border across the India
Tibet border and one of the uh trading
points is going to be Lipul and Nepal
says that Lipool is our territory. I
don't know what is the
I mean what's the basis of this claim or
whatever but they claim it's our
territory and that's why they're
opposing it. That's that's about it. Uh
Jay Shankar Sharp responds look that's
okay. I don't care about ver verbal
verbal exchanges.
Uh if you have a problem buying oil from
India, don't buy it. Okay, that's okay.
See, the relations are in such a
position that you can afford to
uh indulge in sharp rhetoric. In the
past, an Indian foreign minister would
not have uh commented so so sharply
about u about a US president or about
the United States. Won't have happened.
But today relations are in such a such a
situation that yeah go for it. So at the
end of the day it's all words. What
really matters is what happens on the
negotiating table. What are what
actually transpires
in in in in real terms not in terms of
words. We Indians love to focus on what
this guy said and what that guy said.
And our foreign minister gave a gave a
sharp response and our foreign minister
gave very harsh words. Who cares about
words? At the end of the day our economy
needs to grow.
Okay. That's what matters. all these
words blah blah blah it's all fine how
does the relationship progress that is
important are we going to at some point
in time reach a trade agreement with the
US a trade deal Trump has been pushing
for a trade deal is that going to happen
that's more important than what Jashanka
said
um so yeah and and Mr. Dr.
response is absolutely correct. I mean
if you have a problem buy from buying
oil from India, don't buy it. Buy it
from somewhere else. So what the deal is
is that India is importing crude oil
from Russia, refining it and then
selling it to other countries like the
US, like the EU nations or whatever. And
if Trump has a problem with that, well
then stop buying it. That's that's all
he's saying.
Basar Gupta says why opposition votes
against IM?
What is IM? I'm not sure about this.
This is about Indian politics. I will
not deal with Indian politics. I don't I
don't talk about Indian politics.
MK says, "Who are more dassinated in
values and culture? Indians or Chinese?
In which communities?
Which developed communities are not
denated in culture and values apart from
Jews?
Dassination.
Now once again I asked myself, is this
geopolitics?"
Of course, dassination and all that it
does influence geopolitics because a
nation with more self-respect behaves in
a different manner. So I will I will
take this. Okay.
Who are more dassinated in values and
culture? Indians or Chinese? I think the
Chinese uh their culture was devastated
by the Chinese Communist Party in the
20th century. Uh the Buddhist culture,
the indigenous culture, all the temples
were destroyed. The Shaolin temple was
destroyed. Its library was burned by by
Chinese idiots by by Chinese Communist
Party workers. Right? But now they have
rebuilt everything and they have made it
more glorious than before. So now
they've discovered the value of their
culture. So the Chinese are today I
would say that rather proud of their
culture. The most Chinese you will find
especially young people are atheists.
They say oh my grandmother believes in
Buddha and all but I have no
understanding of it. That's that's what
they'll tell you. If you meet a Chinese
person, a young Chinese person in their
20s and 30s, my grandmother, if a
Chinese person comes to India, for
example, h and they go to some tourist
place and they'll see a statue of some
some Hindu gods or maybe Buddha. They
may not understand the Hindu gods, but
if they say Buddha, they'll say, "Oh,
oh, Buddha, Buddha. Yes, yes, Buddha. My
grandmother worships." But it is very
strange. I I have no understanding.
Completely dassinated indeed. uh but
they still um
but they still kind of value their
culture and they are proud of their
country. So Indians
who is I think Indians and Chinese are
equally dassinated but the Chinese don't
have an inferiority complex. They have
kind of a superiority complex. The
Indians are slightly less dassinated
perhaps. I would say the current
generation Gen Z is super drastinated.
Super derinated. uh and and the problem
with India is the inferiority complex.
Even if you are let's say
dassinated but if you don't have an
inferiority complex and if you're proud
of a country then you're going to end up
being a more powerful force overall.
So I I would say that the biggest
problem with India is the problem in
India is is twofold. First of all,
draination which is systematically done
at so many different levels and secondly
the inferiority complex. Indians have
this massive inferiority complex. Even
the youngsters
they have it the moment they see a
white-kinned person is like oh sir s you
are better than us you're superior
automatically the thing kicks in for
some reason. Uh so overall the Chinese
don't have it at all. Even the Afghans
don't have it but the Indians have it
for for whatever reason. Um, which
developed communities are not derated in
culture values apart from Jews?
Well, I don't know. You got to ask me to
go around the world. You can discuss
every um does is the US derinated? They
don't have any roots. The US roots are
piracy.
See the the Americans their their values
are Anglo-Saxon values. uh the people
who who colonized the Americas, the
English speaking peoples, there were
multiple waves of colonization, the the
Spanish, the French, the the Anglo, the
English, but the English succeeded,
right? So the the the
Anglo who colonized the Americas were
mainly pirates. The UK used to engage in
piracy slightly, not officially but
unofficially. So you had Jamestown which
was a disaster and then you had uh
Plymouth which was pilgrims and so on.
Um
so are they true to to those roots the
the piracy roots? They kind of are.
Australians are also not derinated.
They're also very true to their Anglo
and piracy roots. Um and yeah you can go
around the whole world and discuss each
country in detail that way.
MK says was China behind Pakistan Russia
Dhba? Possibly could be. It is possible,
but I'm speculating. I don't really
know.
At the end of the day, I I'll not blame
China for that. It was Russia's
decision. Whether it was whether it was
influenced by China or not, it doesn't
really matter from my perspective. My
perspective is that Russia went and did
this, right? So, I don't know. We don't
know for sure who was behind it. Maybe
it was just Russia. Maybe China may have
nudged them in that direction. We don't
know, but it's a possibility.
Zenan says, "Will Trump's tariff policy
lead to the fall of the US?" No. Nope.
Literally, officer Case says, "Is
Pakistan facing an internal crisis in
Kyber, Pakun, Hua? Do you believe we
could see a Taliban incursion into the
rightful Pashon lands?
There there's a problem in the region.
No question about it. Pakistan is facing
problems in Kyber Pakta.
They're also facing problems in
Baluchthan.
Now understand this properly.
The Taliban
are
not a professional army.
Uh they are trying to professionalize
their military but they're not a fully
professional military the way the
Pakistani military is. I'm not saying
the Pakistani military is as
professional and and as proficient as
the Indian military. We saw the the
difference in quality in May operations
in dur. So we don't need to compare
Pakistan with India. Let's let's keep
that out of our minds.
But the Pakistani military still is a
professional military. And if there is
an actual war with the Taliban, the
Taliban will be defeated 100 times out
of 100. Please understand that. Okay? A
Taliban incursion into the rightful
Pashon lands. No. And I'll tell you why.
So most Indians will not know about
this. But the Taliban receives a stipend
of between 30 to 80 or maybe 100 million
dollars in cash per week from the US.
You heard that right. The Taliban
receives a weekly stipend from the US.
Various figures have been put between 30
to 100 million in cash per week.
So when you are receiving a stipend from
the US, a weekly stipend,
you are a US vasal in some way. Not in
all ways but in some ways. So you must
know perhaps that before the Americans
handed power to the Taliban, there was a
da dha deal, a deal, a secret deal
between the US and the Taliban. All
aspects of the deal have not been made
public. Only some aspects of the deal
have been made public. There are some
secret closes to the agreement which are
secret.
What what what is that? We don't know.
So the Taliban has an understanding with
the US. The Taliban probably they have
been told that you can take this
country. You can do whatever you wish
with it. You can impose Sharia law. You
can do whatever. But certain things you
you cannot do. Maybe you can't invade
Pakistan. Maybe you you can't allow
Pakistan. You can't allow China to
create the China Pakistan economic
corridor or or their belt and road
initiative through Afghanistan and don't
allow the Chinese to invest in your
whatever sector or whatever that sort of
thing and as long as Taliban does that
they keep receiving this typen from the
US which allows them to run their
country in in some some sense of
comfort.
So when the Taliban has such an
arrangement with the US and when
Pakistan is a US vasal, do you imagine
that Taliban will end up invading
Pakistan? Not going to happen.
Okay.
Rishi VMA says, "Can India's
multi-alignment survive US China clash?"
Well, there's not much of a US China
clash happening right now.
So Trump started his trade war with 125.
Yeah, I think it was 125% tariffs
eventually on China. I think it started
with 100% tariffs, then it it he raised
it to 125. Right now I'm not sure. It's
it's it's it's a different number now.
So right now the US and China are not
clashing. You see they have reached some
kind of compromise for now and the
tariff numbers are low
lower than definitely lower than 100%.
Um eventually there could be some kind
of showdown between the US and China. It
depends whether it happens or not. Will
there be a China Taiwan showdown? Will
there be a technological showdown?
I think it's in both nations interests
not to have a hot war.
So I think this competition, this
rivalry between the US and China will
play out in different sectors in
different ways. Mostly it's
technologydriven rivalry.
Uh
and if there's a clash, a war, then you
stay out of it, right? If you're India,
you stay the hell out of it. You say
this is none of my business. I'm I'm out
of it. You guys carry on. That's what
you do. So you you carry on. So can
India's multi-alignment?
I don't care about multi-alignment. And
I just care about India. Does India
survive a US China clash? Absolutely.
And India's policy of multi-andignment
will also continue. So yeah, overall it
will it will.
Nelas says as India has technology to
put a helicopter on what is that B? One
second. What is that?
Okay. A spacecraft. Okay.
Uh on the on the moon and on Mar in Mars
orbit. Uh this implies India can make
ICBMs as part of will as per will. Is
that true? Also, if the Earth's
perimeter is 40,000 kilometers, how can
a 13,000 ICBM reach a desired target on
Earth? Okay.
What is the Earth's perimeter? Um, let's
look it up. Let's look it up. Okay.
Let's look up Earth's perimeter.
Um,
Earth perimeter.
Earth perimeter is 40,000 km. Okay,
fantastic. 40,000 km. All right.
U first of all, let's address the first
part of the question first. India has
the technology to put a spacecraft on
the moon and in Mars orbit. It mean it
means India can make ICBMs.
Of course, India can make ICBMs. You can
use the PSLV as an ICBM.
You can of course you can use the PSLV
as an ICBM. But understand that when you
are building the PSLV, it takes a lot of
time.
And the PSLV has multiple stages. Some
of these are liquid fueled. If you want
to use a rocket as a weapon, you want
solid fuels fueled rockets because
liquid fuel will evaporate. You can't
keep liquid fuel in a in a rocket for
long because it is cryogenic. It is at
very low temperatures. Liquid oxygen
liquid n liquid. So not not hydrogen.
Usually it's oxygen or or or hydrogen or
some hypergolic fuel or whatever.
Hypergolic fuel is possibly solid fuel
but see liquid fuel is generally liquid
gases.
You can't store liquid gases for for a
very long period of time. So a PSLV can
be used as an ICBM but in in in warfare
if it is ever used ICBMs if you want
them to be reliable and available on
demand at 5 minutes notice you want
solid fueled ICBMs and that's a little
more challenging. I think India already
has the technology to make an an ICBM, a
missile that can reach any part of the
of the world with solid fuel. Yeah. So,
India anyway has ICBM technology. No
question about it. Um parameters 40,000
km. How can a 13,000 km ICBM reach any
target on on the earth? See, it's 40,000
km at the equator. At higher latitudes,
at lower latitudes, it's going to be
different.
So, it's a it's just a question of
geometry. But if you take an actual
globe and you point and you and you and
you map a straight line a curved it's
not it's it's it's it's not ukidian
ukidian geometry anymore. It's Rhymanian
geometry because it is curved surfaces
but if you actually calculate it it's
going to be it's going to be enough to
reach reach any desired location of
importance.
Okay.
Next. Oopsy where are we?
Uh where are we? I kind of lost.
Give me a second. Okay, fine.
Okay. Sak Sax Sham says Saksham I guess
says if the US dollar loses dominance in
2030 years, which currency will lead
globally?
If the US dollar leads loses dominance
in 2030 years, which currency will lead
globally? the euro, the Chinese yuan or
a new digital multilinational currency.
We have no idea. In 2030 years, they may
have new currencies.
Can't say. Can't say. The euro no chance
the euro will do it. Why? Because the
euro is the currency of u a coalition of
vasals which is led by the US. If the
dollar loses dominance, then the EU will
fragment. If the US empire becomes weak,
then the European Union will no longer
stay cohesive because it is held
together by the by the US. Most of you
will not be able to see it that what are
you talking about?
What are you talking about? The EU is
blah blah blah. The EU is held together
by the US. The moment the US becomes
weak, the EU nations will go in their
own directions and all the old European
rivalries will resurface and their heads
will reappear.
So if the US dollar loses dominance in
2030 years which means the US empire
becomes significantly weaker then the
euro will also collapse then it could be
perhaps the Chinese yuan the Russian
ruble maybe the Indian rupee um digital
currencies mult multinational currencies
I'm not sure about that multinational
currencies are usually currencies that
that benefit only one nation actually so
activa thank you very much. Thank you.
No question but thank you.
And Activa once again um
this is not a geopolitics question. How
do I find your standalone Amazon Kindle?
I don't have one yet. Once I start
publishing, you will have it and I'll
I'll put the links out. All right. All
right. Thank you, sir. I'll put the
links out on the on the community page.
You you'll find it then at that point in
time.
Prane Kumar says how to counter mass and
social media scops in India.
Um how to counter that? Well, you know
these social media scops are done at the
government level.
So if it has to be counted, it has to be
countered at the government level. What
governments do is is that they create
these massive numbers of automated
accounts, fake accounts,
also called bots.
Okay.
maybe a 100,000 bots and they all
amplify a certain message and they also
will will uh you know pay certain
influencers let's say influential people
with let's say large numbers of
followers they'll pay such people to
further amplify the narrative. So you
have some people on your payroll, some
reasonably prominent people. You will
also pay some people from some think
tanks or whatever to write and say good
things about uh or bad things about a
certain country and then you will have
all these little fake accounts to
amplify that and that's how you can
trend hashtags and and and do all kind
of stuff. So it is done at multiple
levels. So how do you counter that? By
doing it yourself in the opposite
direction. So I would have expected the
the government of India the Modi
government to have done this by now but
they simply haven't it doesn't look like
they have uh chosen to take up you know
the social media battlefield because
clearly there are no bot accounts or all
these massive influential you know scops
or whatever that are pro- India. It's
always anti-India. So it's like it looks
like India has decided not to play the
game at all. So what can I say?
Ashoto Sony says if brrics decides to
launch a bricks currency today, how will
it impact the global trade and what are
the consequences of it? If there is a
harmonized RAS group, how will it help
the global trade?
There's not going to be RA group anytime
soon for reasons that I just explained
some time ago. If bricks decides to
launch a bricks currency, how will it
impact the global trade and what are the
consequences of it? If bricks launches a
global a currency a unified currency
it's going to be a much more powerful
currency than all the other currencies
individually
so it will certainly impact glo global
trade and and it will be a significant
challenge to the US dollar because see
if you if you look at bricks versus G7
if you look at the cumulative GDP of the
BRICS nations and you look at the
cumulative GDP of the G7 nations which
includes the US bricks is now larger
it is now larger. So if the BRICS
nations do come together and create a
single unified currency, it's going to
be overall
very impactful and a significant
challenger to the hgemony of the US
dollar. And if the BRICS nations decide
that we will only trade in the BRICS
currency and other nations uh let's say
global south nations third world nations
whatever you want to call them they also
feel tempted to do that then it could
end up very quickly
raising a big question mark on the US
dollar he hedgemony and its status as
the global reserve currency and that
will lead to an all-out economic war
maybe even military tensions because the
US will take it take it lying down.
If if a BRICS currency is launched, the
US will possibly take military action
against the weaker BRICS nations.
Possibly that's a real possibility.
Brazil for example, Brazil is is a
sitting all the all the Latin American
nations are setting ducks for the US.
They're all US assiles.
So if this happens there will be severe
consequences for the weaker nations in
BRICS. Brazil may undergo regime change.
Brazil may even have military action on
it. Uh which are the other members of
BRICS? Let let's let's quickly Google it
so that I don't do any guesswork.
Um
BRICS list of BRICS nations. Let's see
this.
BRICS countries.
Which are the BRIRS countries? Brazil,
Russia, India, China, South Africa. Then
there's Egypt, Ethiopia, Iran,
Indonesia, and the UAE. Well, if a BRICS
currency is launched, then will the UAE
decide to only trade in the in the BRICS
currency, then it will face immediate
and severe consequences from the US,
Indonesia. Well,
Indonesia cannot stand up to the US.
Okay. Uh Iran will will face severe
difficulties. Ethiopia will be
decimated. So it's going to be severe
consequences. The US will not take this
stand sitting down and they will launch
punitive action on at least the weaker
bricks BRICS nations.
Geopolitical says when do we get a super
chat episode for non- geopolitics
topics? I if if you want one I could I
could do it. I I I can do two
um episodes in a week. Ask a Bijit
Saturday, Sunday. If you want non-
geopolitics topics, well, let me know in
the in the in the in the not in the live
chat, in the comments later when the
stream is over. Let me know. If you want
non- geopolitics topics, I I could do
that. I'll be happy to. Yeah. All right.
Rohan Suna says, "I know many businesses
in India which are on the verge of
bankruptcy because of US tariffs. Don't
you think we should conclude the deal
fast? What deal given to the US?" See
what does We have to ask ourselves this
question. Okay.
What is it that the US wants from India?
They want a deal. But what kind of deal?
What kind of deal do they want? This is
what Trump wants. He wants India to to
live to levi 0% tariffs on any American
export. That's what he wants. Which
means that we can't tax anything that
comes from the US. It has to be sold in
India at the market price in the US at
whatever the US companies decide that
price. The government cannot have one
pesa of revenue from that. That's what
the US wants. It means that you open up
the entire Indian
market to you to US companies entirely.
So we become an importd driven market.
What will that do? Tell me.
US goods, it's true, will most likely be
superior to Indian goods and they will
be available at super competitive prices
in India. Then what will happen is that
the Indian customer will only buy
American imported products which will
destroy India's economies uh India's
India's industries.
So you think that some businesses in
India are on the verge of bankruptcy
because of US tariffs. Once you once you
do a trade deal with with Donald Trump
the way he wants then all businesses in
India will go down. Do you understand
that?
Have you thought of that sir?
Everything will go under. India's
manufacturing sector will be shut down,
locked, over, finished
and then the the Indian agricultural
sector will also be decimated because
the US wants to dump their agricultural
produce in India.
So then you will get agricultural
products from the US that come in at the
same price maybe cheaper prices than
Indian agricultural products. American
potatoes at 10 rupees kilo but Indian
potatoes are 20 rupees kilo.
Hypothetical example, American tomatoes
at 5 rupees kilo but Indian tomatoes are
20 rupees kilo. What will it do then? It
will destroy your farming sector and
their agricultural products are full of
GMOs, genetically modified organisms. So
it will sicken all Indians the way
Americans are sickened. Go to the US and
see how Americans live. They pop pills
five, six times a day. All Americans,
most Americans are obese. You will, you
will have the same problems in India.
their dairy products will come and
destroy India's dairy product India's
dairy industries and their dairy
products they're horrific they feed
their cows
things that should not be fed to cows
okay so you will be consuming that sort
of thing
do you want that so right now if some
businesses are on the verge of
bankruptcy because of US tariffs if we
do a trade deal on Donald Trump's trump
Donald Trump's term terms everything
will be bankrupt. Please understand that
you people.
Vive Singh says why are we looking to
the west for jet engines not to Russia
who are more likely to offer us source
code NATO infiltration and ministry of
defense really NATO infiltration in
Ministry of Defense is it okay let's
address that
see
we have a pages aircraft and we want jet
engines for that correct Yes.
So we want jet engines which will fit
properly on the theas aircraft.
So the the aircraft was built keeping
the American GE General Electric engines
in mind 404 or 414 or whatever it is.
Our designers built the aircraft with
American engines in mind of a certain
shape and size.
Now that the the design is done and we
are already in series serial production,
you can't now say that okay now we will
change the shape and size and parameters
of the whole aircraft which will be
another 10ear design which will be
another 10ear process to change
everything.
So we want now that there's a problem
with American engines they're not
selling us sending us the engines or
whatever despite having taken the money
so we want a replacement engine.
The replacement engine has to be the
same parameters, the same same size
as the engine that the aircraft was
built for.
The Russian engines are ginormous. If
the GE engine is this size, the Russian
engines are that size, that size, huge
beasts of engines. They are super
powerful and all, but they are they are
designed for gigantic aircraft like the
Sukoy 30. If you compare the size of the
Sukoy 30 with the tjas, the the just
looks like a sparrow. The sukoy looks
like a big eagle. Huge size difference.
So the Russian engines are all designed
in that manner. They are gigantic
engines, huge bulky engines, very
powerful. Sure. Now if you if you ask
the Russians, okay, please design
smaller engines for us, that will be a
10, 15 year process even for the
Russians.
So then why do that? You can't. I know
the Russians are more reliable
compared to maybe NATO nations possibly
but the engines are incompatible with
the aircraft that we have in mind the
future AMC and whatn not so that's why
we are not going for that and we are
going for probably Safhan the French
manufacturer
excuse me Rishesh says is North Korea
really as brutal as the western media
portrays Is it? Or is it because it
refuses to bow down to bow down to
America?
I have no idea how North Korea really
is. It's a nation that's closed off.
It's like a walled garden. There's a
wall around the garden. Inside the
garden, you may have nice things, you
may have bad things. We have no idea.
And even if you actually visit North
Korea, you may not see the North Koreans
are very suspicious of of uh of
travelers of of of outsiders. So if you
do visit North Korea, you will be shown
only some locations in North Korea. You
will not be allowed to travel everywhere
and you will always have a minder or two
minders with you. So that's how it is.
So how do I know how North Korea really
is? It is definitely true that the West
demonizes countries that are not aligned
with it like it demonizes India, right?
The portrayal of India on social media
is terrible, isn't it? It's terrible.
The Western media portrays India in very
poor light.
So I suspect that the same could be true
for North Korea as well. So it's
possible that North Korea may not be as
brutal or as whatever they the way it is
portrayed in the Western media. Maybe
it's much better, but I don't know. We
don't know because it's it's closed off.
So can't really say, but it's pretty
likely it will not be not the way the
Western media portrays it. I'm pretty
sure of that.
Godliness says the US under Trump is
becoming even more mighty.
Europe plus UK is now heavily investing
in arms. Do you believe the Anglo-Saxon
Empire is rebuilding itself again? Are
we moving towards imperialism again? So
the US uh empire's behavior, the Trump
regime's behavior is that of an empire
in the past.
So the US has always been an empire but
they always pretend to be a democracy.
They always pretend to be an ordinary
nation and the leader of the free world
and all that stuff. But under Trump,
they have thrown away all those
pretenses. Trump is behaving just like
an emperor or a king would. He is
bullying all his vasals. He has tossed
aside the World Trade Organization and
its rules. Those don't matter anymore.
Right? And he is dealing with each
country individually. You know, for you
this much tariff you for you 30%. For
you oh you're Pakistan 19%. you India
very bad 50%. And that sort of thing and
they're threatening 500% tariffs on
India. So what what are they trying to
achieve? They are completely upending
the existing global economic order which
they created. They created the global
economic order. Now they are undoing it.
Right?
Why is it that they are doing this? Is
it because they feel like they're super
powerful? I think they are less powerful
comparatively than they were 20 years
ago. 20 years ago the US was
unchallenged. It was the only
superpower. Even today it's the only
superpower but today it has competitors
like China and Russia. In 2005 China did
not figure in the conversation. Neither
did Russia.
So the the US 20 years ago was way more
powerful than it is today. Comparatively
comparatively it did not have the
challenges it has today. So today the US
seems to be less confident than it was
before and that's why it's trying to
completely reshape the world order and
bifurcate the world order. It's us
against them. America and Vas versus
China and whoever else. That's what
they're trying to do. Is it becoming
more mighty? I don't think it's becoming
more mighty. But yeah, they they are
becoming more more combative.
U they are becoming more more harsh
towards towards their allies and vasals
or they are treating their vasals very
badly. Recently uh all the EU the major
EU leaders were humiliated by being trot
troted out um to sit like obedient
school children in front of Donald Trump
who lectured them all and that was this
was made into a big media spectacle. All
the EU leaders sitting meekly in front
of Trump. So so Trump is behaving like
an emperor but Trump like I said has
kissed the ring. So this is all being
done by the deeper powers in the US
because they are now feeling less
confident about the way the world is and
they are worried about China's
technological rise and they are also
concerned about the potential future
rise of India. So is the Anglo-Saxon
Empire rebuilding itself again? No,
there's no rebuilding. It's already
built, right? They're trying to preserve
what they have.
See the the the global economic order,
the so-called rules-based world order
was was compared to what Trump is doing
now much fairer
and the US was concerned that the our
enemies are using our rules and the
order we created to enrich themselves
and to strengthen themselves. So let's
destroy this order and let's create an
order that will work only for us for our
benefit and that's what they are doing.
So we are not moving. Yeah, we are
moving towards imperialism. More
imperialism, a more naked imperialism.
We are we are witnessing that now. Trump
is behaving like the emperors of old
days. Exactly.
Dus Putra says, uh, many of your
deductions have turned out to be right
and I've been watching though you since
first episode. Thank you. Thank you. Uh,
thank you very much. Um, but for some
reason I don't I don't even get one of
your video suggestions in my feed. I
hope you do well. A lot of people are
telling me this. Uh, yeah, it it is what
it is. Look, uh, it's it's true. It's
it's now I think everyone's noticing it
that the channel is stuck at a certain
certain point.
Look, it's not in my control. So, I
don't worry about it. Okay? Uh, let the
powers that that are do what they want
to do. And uh, it doesn't concern me. I
I'll continue doing what I what I'm
doing. I I'm being told by so many
people that my notifications never reach
anyone anymore which is pretty
interesting because people some people
do ring the you know the bell icon and
all that so that they are notified.
Anyhow it is what it is. It's not in my
control so I am least concerned and it
doesn't affect me at all. I I'm going to
continue but thank you so much for being
a longtime viewer. I really appreciate
that and I hope you do well too. Please
continue doing well sir. Thank you so
much.
Path says Trump kissed the ring is
puppet of the deep state but thinks but
did things only to win a Nobel Prize
that sounds self-contradictory or is the
deep state making fantasy real using
Trump.
Why is it contradictory? Why he's doing
everything the deep state wants him to
do but as a reward he wants a Nobel
Prize. What is so contradictory about
that sir?
What is contradictory?
I don't understand.
Right. He Trump see Trump was the right
guy for the right time. Trump if you see
his old interviews from the 1990s
he used to talk about tariffs that we
need to impose tariffs on our nation. If
I was the president I don't have any
political ambitions but if I was in
charge I would use tariffs to do this do
that. He used to talk about tariffs in
the 1990s. So he's always been a tariffs
kind of guy.
And now the the deeper powers in the US
have seems to seem to have decided that
he is the right guy for the right time.
He loves talents. Okay, let's use him to
achieve what we want. The Chinese are
using the system we created, the
rules-based so-called rules bas based
world order to make themselves powerful.
So let's completely revamp the order,
the economic order and make it such that
the Chinese can't use it anymore to to
to benefit themselves. That's what
they're doing.
And so that's what the US is doing
through Trump.
So Trump is doing that. But he also has
personal ambitions. He wants he wants a
reward. He wants this big He has the
money now. He also has the power. But he
wants prestige. If Barack could get it,
I should get it. I ended so many more
wars than Barack. That sort of thing.
Okay. So there you have it. Yep.
Okay. What's next?
uh path says
it's a different path. Okay.
Uh hypothetical but can't be ruled out.
What if the US puts a trade embargo on
India
and seizes the forex of RBI?
How can the US seize the forex that
belongs to the RBI
foreign exchange? India's foreign
exchange reserves will be in India,
right?
How how will they come and take that
without invading India?
Trade embargo is a different story.
Seize the forex of RBI. How how do you
do that?
Yeah, that doesn't really uh work out.
Foreign exchange reserves means you have
that foreign exchange within the
country,
right? It's not sitting somewhere in the
US that they can take it. So they can't.
Morti tumuluri, thank you so much, sir.
Very nice of you. Thank you.
Prat Prattard Dana Prattard Dana says,
"I'm sorry if I've pronounced your name
wrong, sir. I apologize for that if it
is the case." The question is, uh, it
looks like China and Brazil have hurt
American farmers badly with soy trade.
Okay. I have not kept an eye on the soy
trade, so I'm not aware of this. uh what
may have they what may have they done?
China and Brazil have American farmers.
So when it comes to Brazil, if you look
at the map, if you if you if you go to
the map and see the satellite images,
you will see that the Brazilians
have huge land resources.
Okay, let's go to the map. We will go to
Brazil.
Huge nation. Let's go to the satellite
and you'll see huge huge patch of green.
Most of Brazil is green. It's the Amazon
forest. Okay? And a lot of the Amazon
forest as you can see will now be under
a state of encroachment by farmers.
Anywhere you see, you'll see farms. This
was formerly forest.
As you can see, this is now farmland.
Huge patches of the forest have been cut
down to create farmland. And you will
see this encroachment all over the
place. So these are Brazilian farmers.
This may not look like farmland perhaps,
but these are maybe future farms. Uh
whichever way it is, there's a lot of
farmland that's emerging out of the
Amazon rainforest. And much of this
farmland is is is dedicated to uh
soybean plantations. So the soybean
plantations, let's see, is this a farm?
Could be. Could be. This looks very very
Yeah, could be. My point is the soybeans
that are planted in Brazil, they are
used what are they used for? They are
you they are sold to American
uh the American animal agriculture
industry, the American beef industry.
Okay. The Americans uh they slaughter
millions maybe hundreds of millions of
cattle cows every year and those cow for
meat obviously and those cows are
usually fed soybean a soybean based diet
and uh men much of this this soybeans
this soybeans comes from Brazil. I don't
know about China.
Uh but yeah, see the Brazilians have so
much land. They can always clear more
rainforest and plant more soybeans and
send it send it to the US. And I'm sure
they do it at a cheap price. So maybe
that's that's the deal perhaps. I don't
know about the Chinese. Are they also
exporting soybeans to to the US? Um I've
heard about Fenton Fentinil. I don't
know. We don't know what soybeans, but
now with the with the tariffs, it will
be harder for them to do that. Yeah,
Arnab Banerjee says, "What's your
opinion on Sergio Gore, the new uh US
ambassador appointee to for India and
his main reason for coming to India?"
Well, see, uh Eric Garcetti was the
Biden appointee. He was the governor to
sorry, not governor. What am I saying?
Ambassador to India, viceroy, ambassador
to India during the Biden regime. He's
gone back. He's done. Uh now Trump wants
to have his handpicked guy as the
viceroy to India or ambassador to India.
Um so he has appointed one of his close
minions Sergio Gore uh who will
eventually be in Delhi and he has also
appointed him as a special something for
South Asia and Central Asia and all
that. So what's the purpose to to of him
coming to India? Uh well one of the
purposes is to keep an eye on what's
happening in India. Secondly it is to
rehyenate India and Pakistan.
So Trump wants to elevate Pakistan.
Elevate. Elevate Pakistan. Invest in
Pakistan. Strengthen Pakistan. Elevate
Pakistan. And Trump at the same time
wants to bring India down. Bring India
down. So that you can bring India and
China and Pakistan at roughly the same
level. At least from his perspective.
From his perspective. Yeah. India,
China, India, Pakistan, same thing. So
you rehyer in India. Wherever you
mention India, you also mention
Pakistan. Wherever you mention Pakistan,
you also mention India. In all your
official communications, you always
mention the two nations together. So you
are rehyenating India and Pakistan. The
objective overall of the US policy is to
contain India
because India is the only large economy
that is projected to not have a
recession in the next 20 years. It's the
only large economy that is poised to
grow at at a significant rate GDP growth
for the next 20 years at least. And if
that happens, even if India grows at 6%
per year, even then in 20 years, it
becomes a significantly larger economy
than it's today and that will obviously
transform India into a whole different
sort of entity, a whole different beast,
potentially a challenger, a future
challenger for the US. So they don't
want that to happen and they want to
take action right now to ensure it
doesn't happen that 20 years down the
line they are not in the situation that
India is emerging as a new power which
can challenge them. So all of that for
that you need people in in in the right
places people in Delhi people in other
places who can keep an eye on things and
do things. So the US has this policy
right they have the policy of of of uh
subn subnational diplomacy in India
which means that their embassies and
consulates will engage diplomatically
with not with the Indian government but
with state governments certain state
governments and the objective is to
create more divisions in India. The
Americans fund religious uh conversions,
industrial scale religious conversions.
They they they fuel separatist soft
separatist activities. They this they
want to create divisions based on
language, based on cast, based on
culture, based on um religion, based on
politics, all these things. The US are
past masters at this that they they have
perfected the the color color revolution
playbook and in the next few years maybe
two three years they may want also to
have some kind of regime change in India
because Mr. Modi is very inconvenient.
He's standing straight. He's not bowing
down. He's not caving in. So Mr. Sergio
Gore will probably oversee all these
operations. So there you have it sir.
Vikash visak kaya says how did the
rostill family become so rich and power
powerful? Is there a replacement for
banking systems? I I don't know. I have
not studied the history of the rosel
family. I've heard all kinds of stories
about them. I until today I have not
studied their history. So I will not be
able to answer your question anyway.
It's a historical question. So yeah. All
right. Sorry about that.
Mortit Tubaluri says how do you see
comments from Nimi
Nimki on tariffs feedback if you don't
speak of Indian political situation then
how do we assess a coup situation recent
stunts from somebody okay I'm not sure
what is nimi
how do I see comments from nimi on
tariffs
feedback If you don't speak of Indian
political situation, how do we assess a
coup situation?
Um I'm not really sure what you ask.
What is nimi? First of all,
nimi
and look okay. So I am not able to
understand what nimi is. Okay. First of
all, um I don't speak of Indian
political situation. I don't I don't
talk about internal politics. I talk
about geopolitics, external politics.
How do we assess a coup situation?
There's no cool situation in India right
now. Maybe there there are plans for the
US to eventually attempt a regime change
of some kind in India which would
involve domestic politics obviously
because you in India you can't do a
regime change through the military.
India is not that the that sort of
country. It's not that that sort of
system. If you study how coups are
executed you will understand that there
are certain conditions that need to be
in place in a country. a certain set of
circumstances need to be satisfied for
the coup for the country to be such that
it is susceptible to a coup and those
conditions aren't satisfied in India. So
you can't have a military coup in India.
It just won't work.
So what's the alternative? The
alternative is a regime change operation
like something that takes time. So you
can co-opt or subvert the electoral
democracy in the country. You can
influence the voters. you can perhaps
influence the voting the voting
mechanisms or god knows what and
influence the sh the state of election
the the result of elections or if it's a
country with a coalition government you
can try and break up the coalition
government by um giving inducements to
some coalition members hypothetically
completely hypothetically I'm talking
and then you can maybe hypothetically if
some opposition parties are aligned with
you hypothetically then you can use that
to create misin information spread
misinformation misinformation
hypothetically these are the things you
can do that's what I can tell you I have
a standing policy I don't talk about
Indian politics so I will not talk about
actual Indian politics that's just how
it is sorry about that
part says what GDP per capita India
before low or no tariffs
what GDP per capita
India before low or no tariffs.
Are you asking what should be India's
GDP per capita such that Trump cannot
impose tariffs on India? Well, Trump
doesn't care about India's GDP per
capita.
It has nothing to do with India's there
is no correlation between India's GDP
per capita and the tariffs that Trump is
imposing. Absolutely no correlation
whatsoever. So even if India's GDP per
capita is let's say $1,000 or sorry
$10,000, it will make no difference to
Trump. Of course, if India's GDP per
capita is higher, it gives India more
leverage because it means India's
overall GDP is higher. So, what is our
GDP per capita right now? Let me just
see. Okay. Uh, it used to be 2,000
something. Maybe is it 3,000? Let's see.
India
India GDP per capita in USD
$2,700 in 2026. Okay, it's about $2,700.
India's GDP per capita. Now let's say
India's GDP GDP per capita is let's say
$10,000 which is four times that.
It means India's overall GDP will also
be four times that which means India's
overall GDP for that will have to be $16
trillion which is a whole different
beast. So then India will have more
leverage. So I I don't know I can't
really say but for that to happen will
take many years. So
it's actually
see as long as Trump is there there's
going to be tariffs it looks like and it
will have no and India's GDP per capita
will have no bearing on that.
Shivan Bakshi says do you think Pakistan
realistically can launch a nuclear
strike against India? If its masters
tell it to it can
if Pakistan's masters tell Pakistan to
launch a nuclear strike on India it will
do that. So Pakistan when I say Pakistan
will do it it means Pakistan's military
leadership will do it for that to happen
they will first ensure that all their
family members all their assets are
moved outside of the country because you
know if what happens if they launch a
milit nuclear strike on India we know
what happens it can it will do it as
long as the Americans or the masters uh
ensure the safety and security of of the
Pakistani military leadership their
families and all their stolen assets all
the student wealth. As long as that
safety is ensured, Pakistani military
leader leadership will do it even if it
means the complete annihilation of
Pakistan which is guaranteed. Yeah.
Nafrati Chintu says JSR well JSR sir uh
how is Modi dealing with this current
trade crisis as compared to blunders
done by Nehu? Is he repeating the same
or working for his legacy?
Mr. Neu never faced the situation that
Mr. Modi is facing. Mr. Neu never came
under economic coercion from the US.
India is facing the worst
American economic coercion since 1947
today.
That's how bad the relationship is.
India has never faced this level of
economic coercion from the US ever
before.
So you can't compare what Mr. Modi is
facing com with what Mr. Neu's time was
because Mr. Nu never faced any of these
issues. The blunders Mr. Neu did you
can't compare that with anything
related to Mr. Modi. Mr. Modi did not
give away the Kabo value to somebody to
Burma. Mr. Modi did not refuse uh
multiple offers of permanent UN security
council membership. Mr. Mr. Modi did not
refuse the offer of nuclear techn
nuclear weapons technology. Mr. Neu did
Mr. Modi did not help China invade Tibet
by supplying Chinese soldiers with rice.
You can't compare. There's no
comparison. All right, we first
understand that. Secondly, Mr. Nu like I
said never faced American economic
coercion the way Mr. Modi is doing
because Mr. Neu his uh economic policy
was to not have any economic growth in
India. 2% 3% growth per year the
Nehuvian rate of growth. Mr. Modi is
trying to grow India's economy as fast
as possible despite all the challenges
he's facing internal problems and all
that. So Mr. Modi is trying to make
India into a real power and that's the
problem he's he's facing that the US
doesn't like it at all. The US is
worried about that. Right? Uh so Mr.
Modi is dealing with it this as best as
he can. The alternative to this is you
become American vasal and you say
goodbye to the econ to the Indian dream.
So Mr. Modi is saying no I will not make
my country an American vasal. We will
stand straight. We will face the the
storm. We will withstand the storm and
we will come out of it stronger. That's
what he is doing. So I I really commend
what Mr. Modi is doing. Now, of course,
India is facing problems
and that's why the opposition apparently
is dancing and and shouting and
screaming from the rooftops. Look at Mr.
Modi's policy. So many problems. Never
had this before. Yeah. Because you never
had any ambition before. If you are
unambitious, you will never face
problems because you are not going
anywhere anyway. It's only when you
become ambitious and you stand up for
yourself that you start facing problems
from the rest of the world because they
are now threatened by you. That's why we
are facing problems. So if you don't
want problems, it means you have no
ambition.
Is that is that what you want? I mean,
I'm not asking Nafra into you, but I'm
asking everybody. Is that what you want?
The moment you stand for something, the
moment you take a stand and you you
decide that I have ambition, I have
goals and I'm going to go for it. That's
when everybody stands against you.
If you are a loser sitting at home and
doing nothing, nobody stands against
you. You'll have the easiest life, a
life of no worth and no value.
RL says, "Do our minister's family
study, live, study, etc." Look, I like I
said, I
Okay, let's take the question. Do our
ministers families live, study, and work
abroad? US EU gives them a leverage and
can be arm twisted compromising India
especially Dr. SJ Shankar.
Do you have to ask me for about this?
I suppose you can do a simple Google
search and find out for yourself. Why
are you asking me this question?
You are you trying to put me in a spot?
Is that what you're trying to do?
I think u
all the facts are searchable.
All the facts of whether any minister
has any family abroad or whether any
minister has uh family members who are
foreign citizens. All of this I think
it's available in the public domain.
Is that potentially a problem for India?
I think I will leave it to all of you to
to judge and decide. That's what I'll
say. Does it give leverage to foreign
countries? I will leave it for you. You
I think you are all wise enough to judge
and decide for yourselves.
That's all I'll say about this.
Mr. James is back. We educated you, made
you literate, yet you harbor deep hatred
for us anglers.
Tea. Tea. We We gave you tea.
Uh James, you see, you did not educate
us. You destroyed our education system.
We had our indigenous education system.
Okay, James, I'll tell you what. Picture
this scene, my friends. All of you,
including our friend, Mr. James. Picture
this scene.
Fire.
Fire that lasts for months.
Verses in Sanskrit that are being turned
to ash. mathematical equations written
in Danagari or or whatever script
turning to ash and returning to the
cosmos.
What is that? That was the destruction
of the Indian education system done
first phase done by the Turks.
So that destroyed our our our records of
history, the records of our history,
right? We had the world's most
sophisticated education system. We
invented the concept of the university.
The world used to come to India to
study. The Chinese, Schwanzang, Fahan,
the Greeks, the Babylonians, the
Mesopotamians,
the Koreans, the Schians,
the people from Subarabumi from
Southeast Asia. Everyone used to come to
India. Schwanzang
walked on foot 16,000 kilometers across
treacherous deserts in frozen mountain
ranges risking his life over and over
again to reach India and study in India.
Okay, we had the world's most advanced,
most sophisticated education system.
The Arabs
acquired their knowledge of astronomy,
mathematics, pharm pharmacology,
toxicology, science,
all of that, algebra, algebra, all of
that from India. And they credited India
for that in their books. Then that
knowledge transmitted was transmitted to
Europe eventually. And the Europeans did
not credit India for any of that. and
all of the European advancements that
eventually happened in science,
astronomy, technology, all of that. Why
did it happen? Because they were
standing on the shoulders of giants, our
ancestors.
Now when the British came to India, we
still had some form of education system
that had continued.
We had a temple-based education system.
Every town, every every city, every
village had temples. And temples were
not just merely places of prayer. There
were places of of of education. That's
where kids got educated.
You learned your basic mathematics,
arithmetic, basic grammar, Sanskrit, all
of that stuff. You you learned it,
purana, mahabara, drama and all of that.
And if you wanted to study further, you
could go to a bigger temple or you could
go to a visha vidal university to to
study. But the vishules were destroyed
by the Turks. So you would go to temples
to study and you still could learn a
lot. The British ended that and they
imposed their their abysmally inferior
education system on India.
The colonial education system which was
designed to pre to prevent Indians from
turning out from from producing leaders.
It was designed to massproduce clerks
and peons. And that's why the Indian
mindset today it's is stuck at the level
of clerks and peons.
There's no leadership level thoughts
coming out of India today because of the
education system that still continues.
So just because you imposed your
inferior
language upon us doesn't mean that you
made us literate
literate. If you genocide a people, they
will harbor some form of hatred towards
you. Now I have no antipathy or hatred
towards the people of England today.
But if some of them come to me and tell
me that we educated you, well that's a
problem for me. I don't harbor hatred
for towards the English. I have I've
been to England. No issues. But some of
the English uh they still have this this
uh
this attitude of superiority. There's
nothing superior about you. Ask what
just read what the Romans wrote about
you. Check it out.
All right. Cheerio James
Spade says, "Sir, I heard that China has
lied about this population which may be
less than one 1 billion being an
authoritarian regime with a one child
policy. They lack do real domestic
demand and thus may stay export
oriented."
Okay. Population, domestic demand,
export oriented. There are multiple
issues, multiple topics here. I I think
it's possible that the Chinese may have
uh kind of exaggerated their population
numbers. I think it's definitely
possible. See, the China's official
population right now is what 1.4
billion. It's possible it may be maybe
1.2 billion, maybe 1 billion. It is
possible. It is also possible that GDP
numbers may be inflated and fake. A lot
of things are possible about China.
Um so it's entirely possible that their
numbers are inflated and they don't
represent the actual u truth on the
ground
fact of the ground. Uh one child policy
yeah that has led to the population
collapse and um true yes that's true uh
they lack real domestic demand.
They do lack domestic demand. I mean
they they have a manufacturing over
capacity.
They have built an economic a
manufacturing base that that is that
represents an over capacity for the
considering the purchasing power of
their population
and that's why they are an export-
oriented economy because they became the
manufacturing base for the entire world
and that's the the trap that Trump has
laid for them that if you impose massive
tariffs on China then they can't export
to the US market then what do they do
with the manufacturing old capacity that
will kind of be a huge problem for the
economy and that's the problem China is
facing and maybe that's why they're
trying to deal with India without
actually resolving any of the real
issues that lie at the heart of the
problems that exist between India and
China and those problems are of China's
own creation so
Achini Anand says does dragging
negotiation favor us in trade deal it
depends see generally if a negotiation
negotiation goes on longer it generally
favors the side that has more leverage
a side see there are two parties in
negotiation this guy and this guy let's
say this is US this is India okay that's
blue is India this is blue this is India
this is the US so now the side that is
more powerful has more leverage and
longer negotiations generally favor them
but if a side is in a hurry If if one of
the parties in is in a big hurry and the
other one is in no hurry then it
generally dragging the negotiations will
favor the one who is not in a hurry. So
it depends but when it comes to a power
asymmetric the US is way powerful India
is much less powerful then any
negotiation will always favor the side
that's more powerful that has more
leverage and even if the negotiation
drags on it may favor the more powerful
side.
CSPV says, "Your opinion on the
recoveration of Nakimov ship?" I have no
idea what that is. Let me check it out.
What is this Nakimov ship? Uh, let's
see. Let's uh ask our friend Google
Nakimov
ship. What is that?
Russian battle cruiser Admiral Nakimov.
Uh SS Admiral Nakamo 25
is third project or land something
battle cruiser originally part of the
Soviet Navy Khalin. It was renamed etc.
Navikov blah blah blah blah blah blah
since 99. It is undergoing repair and
refit to get more weaponry scheduled to
reenter service
delayed till 2024 and it has now begun
factory C trials after repairs and
modernization. Fantastic.
Congratulations Russia. Well, okay. I
don't think it's like a groundbreaking
news or anything. One more battleship in
the Russian army, in the Russian Navy.
Good for them. Maybe it's pretty
capable. All right. Good for them. It's
a boost to their naval power.
Okay.
Pratt Dhana says, "X also hides your
posts despite the bell being pressed."
Well,
yes. I' I've have had pretty interesting
history on social media. I'll tell you
what. Um, for about 3 years, my it was
called Twitter early, right? So, for
about three or four years, I was stuck
on 64,000 subscribers on Twitter
for 3 4 years. 64,000 subscribers.
I I used to tweet a lot back in the day.
I used to get a lot of a lot of
engagement. But my subscribers was
64,000. Prior to that,
one morning, I think it was in 20 18 or
something, don't remember which year it
was. One morning I wake up and I see
that my Twitter following count,
follower count has dropped by exactly
20,000. So in one night they cut out
20,000 of my followers. Gone, vanished.
Few months later, one morning I wake up,
another 7,000 gone. Not 7,000, 223 or
something. Exactly 700 0. So once they
they removed my subscriber count they
reduced my subscriber count by two
20,000 2000 0 few months later it was
700 0 and my subscriber numbers were
stuck after that at 64,000
for like 3 4 years the moment Jack
Dorsey moves out and Elon Musk comes in
my subscribers start growing again so
clearly there was something at play my
it's neither right now 200,000 plus
something.
So is it now that again my posts are
being suppressed? I have no idea. Well,
you see this is this is what happens
when you have foreign platforms. Okay?
So you can't complain about it. These
are their platforms. They own them. They
can do whatever the hell they wanted
with it and uh it is what it is. So my
philosophy in life is very simple. See,
I'm a very simple person. If I if there
is something that's beyond my control, I
don't worry about it. I don't complain
about it. Let it be. You do what you
want. You do what you can. And let the
rest be in the hands of the gods. If you
can't control it, leave it to the gods.
That's all I'll say.
Uh
Anuba Pande opinion on increasing India
Philippines relations. Well, in
Philippines is the Maharlic Islands,
right? Uh it used to be part of the
Chola Empire. They used to be Hindus
back in the past. Today, they don't even
remember that. Uh but that's old
history.
Philippines faces a lot of coercion and
a lot of bullying from China.
Philippines uh has for for the longest
time been a US vasal also which is very
unfortunate for them. It is what it is
once again and uh we have sold them a
few Brahos units and they may be in the
in the market for a few more. So overall
India Philippines are on there's a
significant convergence of interests. So
it's natural that the relationship can
become uh stronger as time progresses
and we should do that. Yeah. So good.
I'm I'm glad. I'm glad. That's my
opinion.
Uh
uh Pratam Sony says, "What is India's
national interest in tips in raising
standards?" Well, two totally different
questions and pretty big questions. Uh
tips in raising standards. Look, I I
cannot give you lectures about raising
standards. I can there are lots of
people who give lectures on YouTube
about you know how to become better a
better version of yourself and how to
become more productive and how to be
more motivated and so on and so forth.
If you want to raise your standards it's
a very difficult process. It's like
climbing a mountain.
It's making small changes and being very
consistent with those changes. It's
pretty and it's it's it's very hard.
Most people don't have the appetite to
do that. Most people are happy being
comfortable the way they are. They want
in their mind they see a different image
of themselves, their true potential. But
that's too hard to achieve. To achieve
that, you have to break all the old
habits and do very uncomfortable things
for a sustained period of time.
So it's difficult. You have to do very
hard things to raise your standards.
It's not easy. Oh, here are five tips to
raise standards. Tomorrow you practice
the you start that and you'll be
immediately higher standards. No, higher
standards means changing your habits and
having new habits and executing them
consistently for several months minimum.
Then you will start seeing seeing
changes. That's where your standards
rise. It's about sustained execution of
difficult things of things that make you
uncomfortable very uncomfortable. That's
raising standards not easy trust me. Uh
what's India's national interest? Well,
to say it in short, the long-term
security, prosperity
and
the security and pro prosperity
what what's the one parameter that's
missing?
Um,
sovereignty,
long-term sovereignty, security, and
prosperity of the people and the nation.
That's the national interest in in in a
nutshell.
godliness says it will take just one it
will take the US just one BJP defeat at
the center to turn us into a vasal
either go for a one party system or just
wait for the day when the Indian PM will
also be dictated at the old office I
completely agree with you
I completely agree with you there's
nothing more to say I agree with you
proud says GDP PPP more which is more
important
um purchasing power overall in the in
the in the context of the entire of the
global world, I would say the GDP is
more important. That's how I see it.
I've always paid more attention to GDP,
less to PPP.
So from my perspective, the way I see
it,
uh GDP is more important. There are
people who will say that PPP is more
important. People who want to portrait
China as as being ahead of the US, they
will say that PPP is more more
important. Um but I think uh that's not
quite the case. The way I see GDP and
not purchasing power parity but the the
other GDP figure that is more important.
Okay. Uh next Duf Patel says why were
wars swift and focused on a nexation at
the time of kingdoms but now are slow
despite advanced weapons.
Uh it's not entirely the case that uh
wars were always swift.
I mean um Google this the 100 years war.
Okay, there have been wars that have
lasted forever. Imagine a series of
conflicts that goes on for a 100red
years.
Uh you've had many extended campaigns,
lots of extended campaigns. So it all
depends on a variety of factors. Uh for
example, see I'll give you an example.
World War I. It begins what? Around
October or something. Uh 20 uh sorry,
what am I saying? 1914. October or
something. 1914.
Um and it was supposed to be over by
Christmas. That is December 25. We will
be home by Christmas. That's what the
belligerents were expecting. But what
happened was that it it went on until
198 1919, right? It went on for a whole
lot of time and it became a ghastly
ghastly war. trench warfare, abysmal
conditions.
Uh so that also went on for such a long
time.
So at that time you had kingdoms and
empires. The Austrohungarian Empire was
one one of the major belligerents and
they essentially started the whole thing
by giving that ultimatum to Serbia,
right? They sent an ultimatum, the kind
of ultimatum Serbia simply could not
agree to because of the wording of the
ultimatum. And eventually and all these
powers, they were planning for a war.
They were planning for a decisive war
for years and it all just happened like
that suddenly in the in the in the space
of 12 days everybody is at war.
Anyway, I don't know why I'm giving you
the history of World War I. If you want
a little more history of World War I,
the period from 19 from 1871 to 1914 was
actually a cold war period which nobody
realizes. It was a cold war period and
during the time all these European
powers were planning and plotting the
next major decisive war which would make
them which would give them the the the
political outcomes they wanted and it
all came together in 1914 in October and
they all thought it'll be over by
Christmas and it turned out to be an
absolute disaster. So my point is that
you know it's not like all the wars is
to be swift and focused on annexation
and all that in the past. No wars could
go on for century for a century in the
past. So yeah, you have to actually look
at history from a broader perspective to
understand the context u in which you
can place today's wars. Today's wars
also follow similar patterns but the
technology has is changed. Even World
War I the technology was very different
from the previous wars. It was like the
trial of completely new kinds of
technologies and and weapons. That was
World War I. It was like it was it was
kind of like today Ukraine war. In the
Ukraine war, we the the the two sides
are are trying all kinds of new
technologies that had never really been
used in a major war before similar to
World War I.
MK says, why do you say communism is a
toolkit that concentrates power in the
hands of a few people? Please don't
ignore as communism played a significant
role in geopolitics. I don't think this
is a question that should be ignored.
Okay.
So
what does communism say? Communism say
that the means of production must be
owned by the people. Right? the uh the
bour the bourgeoisi which is which is uh
the capitalists they monopolize the
means of production and and they they
they they marginalize the proletariat
and they uh extract all value out of the
proletariat out of their time and they
they they keep all the profits
and that that's wrong.
So what needs to happen according to
Marxism is that uh the prolet there
needs to be a a revolution which is led
by the proletariat and the outcome
should be a dictatorship of the
proletariat.
That's what it says. Very nice concept
that the workers of the world should
unite, take up arms and all these
capitalists and industrialists and all
these wealthy people should be built
with.
Yeah. Finished. And take all the wealth
and create a dictatorship of the
proletariat which will represent the
proletariat and work for the
proletariat.
Great concept. Nobody should be rich.
Everybody should have the same amount of
money and everybody should have the time
to do whatever they want. Very nice
concept. What actually happens?
Markx says there should be a revolution,
a revolutionary war that gets rid of the
capitalists and the bourazi, the
parasites.
See, when there is a revolution, a
revolution is by definition a violent
affair. We I think we can agree to that,
right? It's not a saty satyagraha.
A revolution is a violent affair.
When you have a violent affair which is
led by the grassroots people, the
leaders are going to be the most violent
and brutal people.
That is natural.
When you have a violent revolution, the
people who rise to the top will be the
most thuggish people, the most brutal
people, the most power hungry people.
That's one. Second, let's say you
destroy the bourgeoisi and the
capitalist system. Then you create a a
dictatorship of the proletariat.
Did Marx ever say
how will this dictatorship of the
proletariat be created? Will it be
elected democratically?
How will the leaders be selected? He
never said a thing about that
did he? I challenge you all.
Look up Dash Capital.
Look up, look up the communist
manifesto, whatever you want to look up.
How is the dictatorship of of the
proletariat
constructed?
Who's going to be the leaders? Will they
be elected democratically?
How who's going to choose the leaders?
He said nothing of the of the sort. So
what happens is that the leaders choose
themselves.
How do do they choose themselves? The
most violent thugs who led the
revolution
will be the leaders.
Those power- hungry people, those super
brutal people.
That's what happens.
And they end up creating a power center,
a small power center where all the power
is is is is concentrated.
And then they decide what happens to the
workers.
And you will see this play out over and
over and over again.
And in countries like India
or other countries hypothetically,
you will have communist parties that
take advantage of democracy
to play the game of electoral politics
and they will say, "Oh, we are all for
the proletariat and we are all for
Marxism and uh we are all comrades."
But even those political parties will
have something called a polit bureau
which is going to be a small number of
people who control everything and they
push all their cadders out on the
streets to go and do violent things and
face the eye of the police. Same toolkit
over and over again. So if you actually
study communism
then you will understand it's very
different from what you're made to
believe. But for that you have to do
reading. You have to actually read
history. You have to read Daskcap. You
have to read the communist manifesto.
You have to see the history in detail of
places where the communist and Marxist
experiment actually took place. Then you
will understand this. Otherwise, if you
just listen to what your teachers and
professors say, you will be fooled like
millions of Indians are fooled.
Please look it up. Please do your own
due diligence. Please do your own study.
Whatever little I told you just now,
please factch checkck it
from primary sources, not from your
favorite influencer.
Please, you have to do some hard work to
learn things.
Go says if you were a multi-millionaire
say 100 cr net worth and 50 cr liquid
where would you live Delhi or Mumbai?
Why? It doesn't matter
if you have the s of money it doesn't
matter where you live you'll be fine. Do
you understand that if you have 50 cr
liquid you can choose to live wherever
you want you're going to have exactly
the lifestyle you want unless you go out
on the streets well in that case it's
it's the same lifestyle for everybody
the same infrastructure
um doesn't matter I I like both Delhi
and Mumbai Delhi is a wonderful place
Mumbai also has its own great wonderful
strength and all that so I don't know
once I have that much uh 50 cr liquid
I'll let you know
part says uh question was for imports to
India for better what was the question I
don't remember now what was the question
what did you ask
I'll have to look up all the what GDP
per capita India before low or no
tariffs
question was for imports to India for
better products GDP per capita
I I still I'm so sorry sir. I'm so
sorry. I I think um my intelligence
levels are a little low for sometimes I
don't understand questions. I'm so
sorry. I still don't get it. I apologize
parti. Sorry.
Vi man says how will India survive this
coion especially long long run? By
ensuring that we have the right
leadership.
Okay.
India will survive this coercion and not
be a vasal only if we have the light
right leadership in the hot seat in New
Delhi
if the Indian voters decide something
funny
well say goodbye to your sovereignty
that's how India will survive all right
good question good question
SRR thank you so much sir I really
appreciate that thank you
Prashant says impact of India suspending
post postal service to the US so Indian
Post I believe is suspending postal
service to the US except for uh items
that that cost less less than $100 or
something. It's going to impact Indiano
exposed to the US. So I think it's a
signal to the US that we don't care
about your goddamn tires. We ourselves
are going to reduce our exposed to you.
Uh it's going to impact our SM MSMES
medium and small MS medium small
MSMES you know the small industries and
all that. is going to impact them which
is going to cause them pain in the short
term and they will have to pivot very
fast to exporting to other countries.
Yeah.
Uh and Ankita is asking the same
question. What's this suspension of
postal services to the US thing? Is it
only a symbolic postering perhaps?
What's next? Is the situation going to
worsen? Is India ready to absorb
America's sanctioned blows? Well, like I
said, the I I have not really looked
into this in detail what's just
happened. I think I I saw the news
yesterday night or something. Um, so
like I said, uh, Indian Post will no
longer uh send consignments to the US
that have a value of more than $100.
So only if you're sending some small
gift or something to anybody in the US
will you be able to use Indian Post. It
means that you can still use other Kouer
services. Okay, Indian Post, I think
it's a government thing or something.
I'm not sure but whatever. So you can
still use other career services which
may be a little more expensive. So it's
going to kind of impact u Indian
industries and MSMES that are exporting
goods and materials to the US. It's
going to impact them. So maybe it's a
signal to the US and also a signal to
Indian industry perhaps that you know
perhaps you should think of other
markets. Is the situation going to
worsen? I think it's going to worsen.
Trump believes that he can make India
bend. Trump believes that he can make
India cave in and India is not going to
cave in. Mr. Modi is not going to cave
in. So it's going to worsen
u and Trump wants 0% tariffs from India
on American imports while he will keep
the tariffs at maybe 19% or something.
So that's the kind of unequal agreement
he wants and he wants India to be turned
into a dumping ground for American
American products and that is going to
destroy India's economies. So India is
not going to agree to this which is why
the situation is most likely going to
worsen.
uh and India will have to absorb the
American pressure and the American uh u
coercion. Yeah, it's going to it's going
to be it's going to be a tough time for
India the next 20 years and we are
beginning to see that now.
Hyphen two cases. I live in the UK as an
Indian. I faced a lot of racism but now
Indians are looked at with respect. Is
it because of India's growing power and
economy? It means that you've been
living in the UK for more than 12 years,
more than a decade.
I'm pretty sure you're living in in the
UK for more than a decade or at least a
decade. At least a decade. So India was
an insignificant country
from the western perspective. India was
insignificant. India was a third world
country. It still is. But India did not
matter in the world.
It India did not matter at all. But now
India does matter. India is a major
trading power. India is a now a major
economic power. India is a major
military power. India is sending
spacecraft to the moon and to Mars.
India is testing ICBMs. India is doing
very powerful rocket launches. India is
making scientific pro advances,
technological pro advances. India is the
fourth largest economy. India matters
geopolitically. Every single G G7
meeting happens. They they invite India.
India really matters. That's happened
only in the last 10 years.
So India is now looked upon in outside
the the country in a in a different way.
And even if people are unhappy with
India's growth and India's rise,
that unhappiness is also a form of
respect. If if if you are insignificant,
it is disrespect. But if India if people
are upset with you, angry with you, at
least they acknowledge that you matter,
right? Which was not the case before.
So uh when you say that you face racism,
I know exactly what you mean. You go
outside the country especially in
Europe, you will face racism. If you are
not a white person, if you're Indian,
yeah, you are looked upon with you used
to be looked upon with with contempt in
the past. Uh the situation has changed
not in all countries but in in the major
countries for sure. So it is definitely
because of India's uh growing power and
economy. Definitely because of that and
also because of the India's leadership.
Mr. Modi well he has transformed India's
image in in in so many different so many
different ways so all of that matters
yeah
solo leveling says in your opinion how
far behind is India compared to major
world powers across economic military
technological and social dimensions
economically look GDP per capita is 2600
which is abysmal which is like African
countries very far behind cumulative GDP
is fourth in the world soon to be third
in the world. So because even though we
are all individually very poor on
average but cumulatively because of our
huge population we really matter. So we
are very far behind when it comes to
living standards right standards of
living economically we could be we could
do much better with just a 4.9 or
something trillion dollar economy which
is which is small actually even though
we are fourth largest 4.8 8 whatever the
number is 4.5 whatever you want to call
it we should be at least a $10 billion
economy so we have a long way to go
military well we are a very powerful
military actually we are a powerful
military we are a nuclear power and we
have the means to deliver the nuclear
weapons wherever we want we want uh we
have the world's best battle tested air
defense system and uh our our indigenous
uh weapons manufacturing systems are
pretty good and we have we still have a
lot of progress to make But yeah, we are
we are on decent good ground. We need
jet engines and all that. Some some
lacun still exist but overall we are
doing good progress. When it comes to AI
we I don't know where we are. We seem to
be far behind. Quantum computing at
least we have one at least one quantum
computing system now and it's something
that we can definitely work on further
uh technological social dimensions.
Technologically look social dimensions
socially when I say so socially I mean
it's it's living standards. Living
standards are abysmal in India.
infrastructure is is abysmal okay in
those things we are like like African
countries very poor very poor state of
affairs a lot needs to be changed a lot
needs to be improved technologically
look we are okay military we're good
economic we we're decent technologically
we are we are
I mean I mean so much so much more
improvement can be done so yeah that's
what I that's what I would say yes
okay Next sep says who and how India
Bangladesh boundary demarcated. We
helped them get independence from
Pakistan and still we got chickens neck
problem. We hastily took we took that
area 71. I don't know why we have the
chickens neck problem in 71 we could
have solved it once and for all. Why did
we ex first of all in 1947 why did we
accept that? Why? What were our leaders
doing? Were they even leaders for of
India or were they ser serving somebody
else?
to create this chicken neck issue there.
Why? Who the hell were the British to
decide the map? We should have told them
to get the hell out and we will decide
the map. U in 71 also we could have fix
the issue. Now we are where we are.
We'll have to see eventually where how
to solve that problem. It is an issue
for India. It's just 30 km wide at a
certain point which is bad. Yeah.
PrelTP
says opinion on opinion on online safety
act government take over UK. I haven't
seen it. I'm I'm sorry. I don't know
about that. I've heard some some things
but I haven't looked into it in detail
so I can't really uh opine on that.
Rahul Lakman says, "Would you consider
trolling the American immigration system
by applying for a visa?" Now what's the
point? Thank you for the suggestion.
Uh Aladin Chavda,
what's your take on acquiring a foreign
citizenship? I think it's a personal
choice. I would not dissuade somebody
from doing that if that is what they
want. It's entirely your choice.
Entirely your choice. You have to decide
what is best for you and what your
ambitions are. If you feel that you will
do better in life if you acquire a
foreign citizenship, I will say go ahead
and do it. It's entirely up to you. You
are under no obligation to sacrifice
your dreams and aspirations for for any
ideal or anything. So it's entirely up
to you. I I I will not tell people what
to do with their life.
Rajat Chhatraji says what role does
Bangladesh play in future conflicts? How
should India tackle it? Well, as long as
Bangladesh behaves, we are fine. What
role will Bangladesh play in a future
conflict? I don't think Bangladesh will
play any role in any future conflict.
The moment hypothetically Bangladesh
tries to get involved in in a conflict,
it will be trouble for Bangladesh.
India should how should India tackle it?
India should just uh very quietly commun
communicate to Bangladesh if required
that it is best for Bangladesh to stay
out of any conflict involving India.
Just stay out of it and everything will
go fine and smoothly. That's it.
S Bharat says how did the USSR get a
nuclear arsenal despite US victory? You
mean 194 1991, right? when the US was in
no position to take nuclear weapons from
the USSR.
Is that what you're talking about 1991
or are you talking about 1945? 1945 was
a USSR victory.
Okay. And they also had very high
quality nuclear physicists and
scientists and that's why they were able
to develop the nuclear bomb and
eventually the thermonuclear bomb the
hydrogen bomb and they they acquired uh
Nazi rocket scientists which helped
kickstart kickstart the USSR's uh space
program which is also the ballistic
missiles program and that's how it went.
Right.
Okay. We're going to end it very soon
now. So just a few more questions. What
exactly is left and right ideology? What
is the major thing that parties believe
right now that depict somebody something
to be left or right? If you want to talk
about this in the context of India,
leftwing means first of all right-wing
means uh traditionalist people. I
right-wing ideology is more conservative
ideology. It is ideology that is rooted
in Indian culture and civilization. That
is called rightwing in India. So if you
are a Hindu, if you say I am a Hindu and
I'm proud of being Hindu, it means
you're a right-winger. Even if you don't
hate anybody else, even even if you
respect all religions, you'll still be
considered to be a right-winger. So I am
considered to be a right-winger because
I am proud to be a Hindu. I am a Hindu
and I'm proud to be that. I don't hate
any other religion, but because I a
Hindu and I'm proud to be one, I'm
called a right-winger. So in India
right-wing ideology is portrayed as as
being Hindu in character
even if it is very even if the the the
government's government's policies will
be pretty leftwing but as long as they
are proud of being Hindu they will be
portrayed as rightwing. Uh and in India
leftwing means essentially you
not very nationalistic.
Okay.
PrelTP says, "World War I was for
breaking European empires. World War II
was for Wberg banking war to spread
central bank globally and bring fiat
system. Agree?" I have not read about
the Varnber banking war.
The central bank globally bring fiat
system. No, I have not studied that part
of the economic history. So I can't
really say.
Can't really say. Sorry. Sorry sir.
Bankon Singh this is a history question.
We discussing geopolitics today sir
please please please sir please my dear
viewers when when we have a session on
one specific topic let's stick to that
because if I start taking other
questions I'm disrespecting my audience
who has come here expecting a
geopolitics session so please I I
apologize but I can't take this
questionana
says are we hiding our GDP at $210 rupee
exchange our rates our GDP would be 8
trillion is this why the US wants to
stop us. I don't know if we are hiding
our GDP. Today, see the $20 exchange
rate is no longer relevant today. In
2010, what was the exchange rate? I'm
not sure. Maybe 50. I don't know what it
was in 2010. Today, it is all nearly 90.
It's 85 86 87. I don't know what it is.
So, that obviously makes a huge
difference if you are denominating all
the GDP in US dollars. And because the
the US dollar is the world's reserve
currency, all GDP is essentially going
to be denominated in US dollar terms.
Uh, so are we hiding our GDP? I don't
know. If we are hiding it, well, I'll
say good.
Um, is this why the US wants to stop us?
Well, if we are actually hiding it and
they're aware of it, maybe it's one of
the reasons, but I'm not sure if we are
hiding it. The way I see it is let's not
assume things we can't see. What we can
see is that our GDP is whatever 4
something trillion dollars, 4.5, 4.6,
whatever it is. and we are on on on on
track to keep growing at at a decent
rate for the next 20 years that will
bring us into 1015 trillion dollar
territory and that's what the US is
worried about because they've always
worried about India becoming an
imperialistic power. If you see their
cables and communications diplomatic
communications and uh think tank
assessments from the 1950s and 60s you
will see that they were worried that
India will go the way of imperial Japan
which was very frightening for them. So
they still have that worry because India
has the potential but Indians don't
realize it.
Rohit Sharma says what's Mr. Chow's
favorite element from the periodic
table? I've never thought about it in
anyway this is geopolitics session so I
don't know I I don't have a favorite
element from the maybe some of the
radioactive elements perhaps. I don't
know.
AB says what's your views on US develop
deploying warships near Venezuela?
I think it happened yesterday or
something right the news came out. I
really haven't looked into it yet. So I
don't think I have any views right now.
Be before I first look into what exactly
has happened, how many warships have
been deployed and in in reaction to what
has this happened, I'm not really sure
right now because I've not looked into
it. I think it's a very new development.
So I apologize I won't be able to answer
this. Maybe in the next session I can
give you a better answer. I haven't
looked into it. It happened very
recently.
Morphin one says, "How long before the
US breaks our economy?" Never, sir.
Never. They won't succeed. All right.
So, Shan Baratwad, thank you for your
episode. Thank you for everybody. So,
thank you so much all of you. I really
really appreciate all of you. All my
dear viewers, you've been around many of
you from from the first episode which
happened what in June or something 2021
and it's been a while. I can't believe
it's been so long. This is episode 180
281. It's it's a pretty long string of
episodes. It's been a pleasure. It's
been a privilege to have all of you as
viewers to to take all your questions.
It's been a privilege that people ask me
questions. So, I thank you all from the
bottom of my heart for your viewership.
It should be me who's thanking you. So,
thank you all. Thank you so much.
Arraadya Pandit says Ukraine attacked
Russian nuclear base. What can be the
consequences? Russian reaction. Uh when
did this happen? I'm not sure. I haven't
seen this news. But Russia will respond.
There will be a Russian response and
Ukraine will face consequences not very
nice consequences guaranteed.
Juban Dubet says when is India expected
to prioritize the development of an
indigenously built nuclear submarine? I
think we already doing that.
We already doing that. We have
um see we we operate a chakra submarine
which is on lease from Russia
but we have our own
uh nuclear submarine class Ahant class
submarines those are indigenously built
nuclear submarines
and uh yeah it's kind of slow
development because submarines take a
long time to build see the French
suffren class submarines which are the
latest most advanced submarines they
have nuclear submarines uh they
typically take about 10 12 years to
build one submarine okay so it takes
time so we are prioritizing that we have
I suppose limited money for that but we
are doing that we have mini
miniaturaturized the nuclear reactor and
each subsequent submarine is going to be
better than the previous one and yeah we
are we are doing that uh it's always be
nice if we can prioritize it more and
and make it faster hasten it and maybe
turn out more numbers But it is what it
is. So we are developing indigenously
built nuclear submarines for sure.
Okay people that is about it. We are at
the end of today's live stream. We have
gone well in excess of two hours. I
thank you all for your questions. I
really enjoyed this as always.
And uh yep. So today we're done. We're
done for the day today. Thank you so
much everybody for for being on the live
chat for the questions and I look
forward to seeing you all in the next
liveream. Please keep learning, please
keep asking questions, please keep
raising your standards and I will see
you in the next live stream liveream.
Thank you. Take care. Good night, good
day wherever you are. See you soon.
Bye-bye.